Guide to the Guy Johnson Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Guy Johnson papers
1773-1831
GEN MSS 494
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
1.77
(3 boxes) + 1 broadside folder
Correspondence, journals, documents, and maps by or about Guy Johnson. The early correspondence (1773-1774) includes letters from and to Guy's uncle William Johnson, and concern his illness and desire for Guy Johnson to succeed him as Indian Affairs Superintendant. William's correspondents include the Earl of Dartmouth, Secretary of State for the Colonies, and General Thomas Gage. Letters from 1775 concern the loyalty of the Six Nations to the British, and includes an intercepted letter from Ethan Allen, written after his advance on Canada. Guy's correspondents include the Earl of Dartmouth, Daniel Claus, Peter Van Brugh Livingston, and Allan Maclean. Two journals kept by Guy Johnson date from 1775-1776, and 1781. The first journal records his visit to London and return to America on July 29, 1776, and includes an account of Howe's operations on Long Island and the capture of Fort Washington by General Knyphausen. The second journal contains daily reports of Indian raids, news and messages received, and information from prisoners. There are a number of references to Joseph Brant. Johnson's memorandum and account book is dated 1776-1782 and contains his official accounts. Penned at the back are extensive notes about Indian movements. The other journal, written by an unidentified officer posted at Kadaragoras, a settlement built for the Senecas, contains reports on enemy movements. The Other Papers contain formal proclamations by the magistrates of Schenectady and Albany, and by the Mohawks, dated May 1775, stating their mutual wishes for neutrality in the war. A manuscript by Colonel John Butler records the proceedings of 18 councils with the Six Nations and the Canadian Indians, from October, 1775 to June 1776. A manuscript plat map drawn by Guy Johnson of the Townships of Gage and Burton in Nova Scotia is undated. The rest of the papers relate to attempts by Johnson's family to obtain compensation for Johnson's expenses during the war.
Johnson, Guy, approximately 1740-1788
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased by Paul Mellon from Lionel and Philip Robinson, Ltd., 1962. Bequest of Paul Mellon (Yale 1929), 2000.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
GUY JOHNSON (CA. 1740-1788)
Guy Johnson, nephew of Sir William Johnson, served as Deputy Superintendant of Indian Affairs in the northeastern American colonies and became Superintendant in 1774 when his uncle died. In 1775, at the outbreak of the American Revolution, Johnson fled to Canada and sailed to England. He returned to America in 1776, where he directed British raids on settlements in the Mohawk Valley through the end of the Revolutionary War.
Scope and Contents
The Guy Johnson Papers consists of correspondence, journals, documents, and maps by or about Guy Johnson. The collection, spanning the dates 1773-1831, is housed in 3 boxes and comprises 1.77 linear feet. There are three series: Series I, Correspondence, Series II, Journals and Memorandum Books, Series III, Other Papers. Box 3 contains Oversize material.
Series I, Correspondence spans the dates 1773-1831. The early correspondence (1773-1774) includes letters from and to Guy's uncle William Johnson, and concern his illness and desire for his nephew Guy Johnson to succeed him as Indian Affairs Superintendant. William's correspondents include the Earl of Dartmouth, Secretary of State for the Colonies, and General Thomas Gage. Letters from 1775 concern the loyalty of the Six Nations to the British, and includes an intercepted letter from Ethan Allen, written after his advance on Canada. Guy's correspondents include the Earl of Dartmouth, Daniel Claus, Peter Van Brugh Livingston, and Allan Maclean. Two later letters are from Johnson family members and concern compensation sought for Johnson's expenses during the war.
Series II, Journals and Memorandum Books, 1775-1782, is organized into two subseries: Guy Johnson and Others. Two journals kept by Guy Johnson date from 1775-1776, and 1781. The first journal records his visit to London and return to America on July 29, 1776, and includes an account of Howe's operations on Long Island and the capture of Fort Washington by General Knyphausen. The second journal contains daily reports of Indian raids, news and messages received, and information from prisoners. There are a number of references to Joseph Brant, Mohawk Indian chief, who led four of the six Iroquois Indians on the British side in the war. Johnson's memorandum and account book is dated 1776-1782 and contains his official accounts. Penned at the back are extensive notes about Indian movements. The other journal, written by an unidentified officer posted at Kadaragoras, a settlement built for the Senecas, contains reports on enemy movements.
Series III, Other Papers, 1775-1825, is organized into three subseries: Documents, Maps and Illustrations, and Other Papers. Documents contain formal proclamations by the magistrates of Schenectady and Albany, and by the Mohawks, dated May 1775, stating their mutual wishes for neutrality in the war. A manuscript by Colonel John Butler records the proceedings of 18 councils with the Six Nations and the Canadian Indians, from October, 1775 to June 1776. A manuscript plat map drawn by Guy Johnson of the Townships of Gage and Burton in Nova Scotia is undated. The rest of the papers relate to attempts by Johnson's family to obtain compensation for Johnson's expenses during the war.
United States -- History -- Revolution, 1775-1783 -- Personal narratives, British; United States -- History -- Revolution, 1775-1783 -- British forces; United States -- History -- Revolution, 1775-1783 -- Claims; United States -- History -- Revolution, 1775-1783 -- Participation, Indian; Maps (documents); Allen, Ethan, 1738-1789; Brant, Joseph, 1742-1807; Butler, John, 1728-1796; Claus, Daniel, 1727-1787; Dartmouth, William Legge, Earl of, 1731-1801; Johnson, Guy, approximately 1740-1788; Johnson, William, 1715-1774; Livingston, Peter Van Brugh, 1710-1792; Maclean, Allan, 1725-1797; Six Nations
- Correspondence, 1773-1831; Series I; 0.21; (.5 box)
  Scope and Contents
  Series I, Correspondence, is arranged chronologically.
  - 1773
    - Johnson, John to GJ, 1773 Jun 22 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - 1774
    - Johnson, William to GJ, 1774 Feb 13 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Johnson, William to Lord Adam Gordon, 1774 Apr 6 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      Copy in GJ's hand
    - Johnson, William to GJ, 1774 Apr 10 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Johnson, William to William Legge, Earl of Dartmouth, 1774 Apr 17 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Johnson, William to Thomas Gage, 1774 Apr 20 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Penn, John to William Johnson, 1774 Jun 28 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Dakayensere, Isaack to GJ, 1774 Jul 22 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Colden, Cadwallader to GJ, 1774 Aug (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Dartmouth, William Legge, Earl of, to GJ (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Johnson, Guy to John Blackburn. Draft, 1774 Sep 12 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Johnson, S. J., Daniel Claus, and Guy Johnson to Samuel Baker. Draft, 1774 Dec 27 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - 1775
    - Dartmouth, William Legge, Earl of, to GJ (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Allen, Ethan to James Morrison, 1775 May 18 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Livingston, Peter Van Brugh to GJ, 1775 Jun 3 (Box 1, Folder 15)
      Accompanied by draft of letter by GJ in response, dated 1775 Jul 8
    - Dorchester, Guy Carleton to GJ, 1775 Jun 19 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Maclean, Allan to GJ, 1775 Jul 8 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Dartmouth, William Legge, Earl of, to GJ (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Dartmouth, William Legge, Earl of, to Thomas Gage, 1775 Aug 2 (Box 1, Folder 19)
      Copy
    - Le Maistre, F[---?] to GJ, 1775 Sep 13 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - 1776
    - Unidentified to GJ, 1776 Jan 7 (Box 1, Folder 21)
      Copy. Accompanied by a letter from John Blackburn to GJ, 1777 Apr 7
  - 1777
    - Johnson, Guy to [John] Blackburn, 1777 Apr, Nov (Box 1, Folder 22)
      Copies
  - 1782
    - Lansdowne, William Petty, Marquis of, to GJ, 1782 Mar 30 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - 1783
    - Claus, Daniel to unidentified, 1783 Jun 5 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Holland, Samuel to GJ, 1783 Aug 23 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - 1789
    - Chew, Joseph to Colin Campbell, 1789 Jun 22 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - 1831
    - Johnson, Charles C. to Mrs. Campbell, 1831 Jan 12 (Box 1, Folder 27)
- Journals and Memorandum Books, 1775-1782; Series II; 0.1; (.25 box)
  Series II, Journals and Memorandum Books, is organized into two subseries: Guy Johnson and Others.
  - GUY JOHNSON
    - Journal written in Goldsmith's Almanac for 1776. Dec 27 1775 - Nov 16 1776, 1775-76 (Box 1, Folder 28)
      Memoranda written on blank pages at front and back as well
    - "Memorandum & Accot. Book with Government, Officers &c. Commencing in 1776", 1776-82 (Box 1, Folder 29)
      Includes notes on Indian movements at the back
    - Journal, 1781 (Box 1, Folder 30)
      Begins with a brief outline of his experiences in 1778-1780. Map of a fort at the junction of the St. Joseph River and Miami River drawn on inside back cover
  - OTHERS
    - Unidentified. "Book, 1779." Journal of an official at Kadaragoras, New York, 1779-80 (Box 1, Folder 31)
- Other Papers, 1775-1825; Series III; 0.32; (1.25 boxes)
  Series III, Other Papers, is organized into three subseries: Documents, Maps and Illustrations, and Other Papers.
  - DOCUMENTS
    - Report of a suit of James Downes against Guy Johnson relating to land in Schenectady, 1775 Apr 29
    - Agreement of freeholders and inhabitants of the Mohawk District in Tryon County to defend themselves against invaders, 1775 May 11 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - "The Answer of the Magistrates of the Town of Schenectady in the County Albany, to a Speech Made by Little Abraham in Behalf of the Mohawk Indians", 1775 May 24 (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - "The Answer of the Mayor Aldermen and Commonalty of the City of Albany, to a Speech of the Mohawks delivered by one of their Chiefs called little Abraham." Copy, [1775 May] (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - "Answer of the Mohawks to the Speech of the Magistrates &c. of Albany & Schenectady at Guy Park May the 25th 1775", 1775 May 25 (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - Butler, John. "Indian Recoards begun at Montreal the 12th October 1775", 1775-76 (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - List of articles in payment to Piankashaw Indians for land on the Wabash, 1775 (Box 1, Folder 37)
    - "A Treaty of Alliance and Friendship Entered into and concluded by, and between the Governors of the State of Massachusetts Bay, and the Delegates of the St. Johns, and Micmack Tribes of Indians", 1776 Jul 19 (Box 2, Folder 38)
      Endorsed on back: "Surrendered up to Mr. Francklin in 1778 & delivered by Order to Col. Johnson Supt. at Halifax"
    - "Invoice of Indian Stores belonging to Coll. Guy Johnson Sole Agent & Superintendant of the Six Nations that was forwarded at different times to Niagara", 1779 Nov 20 (Box 2, Folder 39)
    - "Roll of Officers &c. of the Indian Department, commanded by Colonel Guy Johnson Superintendant", 1782 Oct 16
    - "Estimate of the Estate Real & Personal of Colo. Guy Johnson, in the Counties of Albany & Tryon, and Province of New York", 1783 Sep 10
    - Memorial of Guy Johnson to the Commissioners appointed by Act of Parliament for inquiring into the losses and services of the American loyalists. Two copies, 1784 Mar 23
    - Deposition of Joseph Chew regarding Guy Johnson's expenditures as Indian agent. Copy, 1788 May 19 (Box 2, Folder 40)
    - Memorial of Mary Campbell, daughter of Guy Johnson, seeking compensation which was due her father at his death. Two copies, 1825 Mar (Box 2, Folder 41)
    - Power of attorney from Mary Campbell to Charles Johnson to sell lands in Canada, 1825 Apr (Box 2, Folder 42)
    - "Case of the Family of the Late Colonel Guy Johnson Superintendant of the Indian Nations in North America." Incomplete
  - MAPS AND ILLUSTRATIONS
    - Hulett, J. "A North View of Fort Johnson drawn on the spot by Capt. Guy Johnson Sir Wm. Johnson's Son in Law." Engraving (Box 2, Folder 43)
    - Johnson, Guy. "Map of the Townships of Gage & Burton in Nova Scotia from the original surveys of Majr. Holland & Mr. Chs. Morris." Manuscript map in pen-and-ink and watercolor
    - "Map of Hudson's River, with the adjacent Country." Printed map, [1778] (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - OTHER PAPERS
    - "Account of Cash Left by Sir Wm. Johnson Baronet at the Time of his Death", 1774 Jul (Box 2, Folder 45)
    - Bond of Abraham Dutchess and James Wells, 1779 Jun 27 (Box 2, Folder 46)
    - Guy Johnson's bills and receipts, 1778, 1788 (Box 2, Folder 47)
      Stored also in: Oversize, box 3, folder 54
    - Johnstone family genealogy notes, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 48)
- Oversize, 1.14; (1 box)
  Oversize contains material from Series II and III, and is arranged in box order.
  - Report of a suit of James Downes against Guy Johnson relating to land in Schenectady, 1775 Apr 29 (Box 3, Folder 49)
  - "Roll of Officers &c. of the Indian Department, commanded by Colonel Guy Johnson Superintendant", 1782 Oct 16 (Box 3, Folder 50)
  - "Estimate of the Estate Real & Personal of Colo. Guy Johnson, in the Counties of Albany & Tryon, and Province of New York", 1783 Sep 10 (Box 3, Folder 51)
  - Memorial of Guy Johnson to the Commissioners appointed by Act of Parliament for inquiring into the losses and services of the American loyalists. Two copies, 1784 Mar 23 (Box 3, Folder 52)
  - "Case of the Family of the Late Colonel Guy Johnson Superintendant of the Indian Nations in North America." Incomplete (Box 3, Folder 53)
  - Guy Johnson's bills and receipts, 1778, 1788 (Box 3, Folder 54)
  - Johnson, Guy. "Map of the Townships of Gage & Burton in Nova Scotia from the original surveys of Majr. Holland & Mr. Chs. Morris." Manuscript map in pen-and-ink and watercolor (Box bsd, folder 55)